Guide to the Sara Teasdale Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sara Teasdale collection
1890-1989
1905-1932
YCAL MSS 746
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(4 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, and other personal papers by or relating to the American poet Sara Teasdale. Correspondence includes several autograph manuscript letters from Teasdale and third-party letters relating to her. Writings include an autograph manuscript diary kept by Teasdale on her first trip to Europe between Feburary and May 1905, six autograph manuscript notebooks, numbered IV through IX, containing poems drafted between 1911 and 1932, and several individual drafts or clean copies of poems and short works. Other materials in the collection include Teasdale's will, notebooks documenting literary submissions and payments received, and photographs. There are photographs of Teasdale, portraits of Teasdale in artwork, the poets Marianne Moore and Genevieve Taggard, Teasdale's friend Margaret Conklin, and her husband Ernst Filsinger.
Teasdale, Sara, 1884-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Sara Teasdale (1894-1932)
The American poet Sara Teasdale was born 8 August 1884 in Saint Louis, Missouri and home-schooled until she was nine. While living in the Midwest, she also traveled to Chicago, where she became part of the circle surrounding Poetry magazine and Harriet Monroe. Teasdale's first book, Sonnets to Duse and Other Poems, came out in 1907. Other works followed, including Helen of Troy and Other Poems (1911) and Rivers to the Sea (1915). After moving to New York City with her husband in 1916, she won the Columbia University Poetry Society Prize and the Poetry Society of America Prize for Love Songs (1917). She published three additional volumes of poetry during her lifetime, Flame and Shadow (1920), Dark of the Moon (1926), and Stars To-night (1930). Teasdale died 28 January 1933 in New York City and her final collection, Strange Victory, appeared posthumously that same year.
Biographical information taken from "Sara Teasdale." Poets.org at <http://www.poets.org/poet.php/prmPID/658>. 24 May 2013.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, photographs, and other personal papers by or relating to the American poet Sara Teasdale. Correspondence includes several autograph manuscript letters from Teasdale and third-party letters relating to her. Writings include an autograph manuscript diary kept by Teasdale on her first trip to Europe between Feburary and May 1905, six autograph manuscript notebooks, numbered IV through IX, containing poems drafted between 1911 and 1932, and several individual drafts or clean copies of poems and short works. Other materials in the collection include Teasdale's will, notebooks documenting literary submissions and payments received, and photographs. There are photographs of Teasdale, portraits of Teasdale in artwork, the poets Marianne Moore and Genevieve Taggard, Teasdale's friend Margaret Conklin, and her husband Ernst Filsinger.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Margaret Conklin Gift, 1905-1932. II. William Drake Purchase, 1912-1989. III. William Drake Gift, 1890-1984. IV. Material from Other Sources, 1905-1931.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Conklin, Margaret; Filsinger, Ernst; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Taggard, Genevieve, 1894-1948; Teasdale, Sara, 1884-1933
- Margaret Conklin Gift, 1905-1932; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. consists of autograph manuscript writings by Teasdale, including a diary kept by Teasdale on her first trip to Europe between Feburary and May 1905 and six notebooks, numbered IV through IX, containing poems drafted between 1911 and 1932.
  Former call number: Za Teasdale.
  Gift of Margaret Conklin, 1942-1945.
  - Diary, 1905 (Box 1)
  - "He I Love Is Far Away," poem, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1)
    Includes "The World Is Watching You"
  - Notebooks, 1911-1932; 2 (Box 1)
  - "The Potter's Wheel," poems, autograph manuscript, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - "The Potters and the Potters' Wheel" by Frances S. Porcher essay, typescript carbon, undated (Box 2)
- William Drake Purchase, 1922-1989; Series II; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Arranged as received by the library.
  Series II. contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers by or relating to Sara Teasdale. Correspondence includes letters from Teasdale and third-party letters relating to Teasdale. Writings include drafts of poems, as well as critical works and an interview. Other materials include copies of Teasdale's will, notebooks documenting literary submissions and payments received, and an original drawing.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 113.
  Purchased from William Drake on the Elinor and Leonard Bernheim Fund, 1989.
  - Vendor description, circa 1989 (Box 3)
  - Letter, autograph manuscript signed, from American Women's Club to Margaret Conklin, 1932 July 26 (Box 3)
  - Letter, autograph manuscript signed (carbon), from Sara Teasdale to Ernst Filsinger, 1929 June 1 (Box 3)
  - "The Self," poem, autograph manuscript, 1927 January 8 (Box 3)
  - "A Song of Silver Slippers," poem, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 3)
  - "Answers to Prof. Lewis About Poetic Composition," notes, corrected, autograph manuscript, 1923 March 13 (Box 3)
  - Letter, autograph manuscript signed, from Sara Teasdale to Mrs. Conklin, 1930 June 4 (Box 3)
  - Letters, autograph manuscript signed, from Sara Teasdale to an unidentified recipient, 1932 March 8 (Box 3)
  - "Sea Gulls at Sunset," poem, typescript, signed, undated (Box 3)
  - Printed card, undated (Box 3)
  - "An Interview With Sara Teasdale," typescript carbon, undated (Box 3)
    Includes note, autograph mansucript, by Sara Teasdale
  - Last will and testament, signed (2 copies), 1930 (Box 3)
  - Notebooks, 1922, 1926 (Box 3)
  - "Statement From Sara Teasdale Concerning the Christina Rossetti Letter Which She Brought Back From England," typescript, undated (Box 3)
  - "Christina Rossetti: An Intimate Portrait," biography, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - Drawing, undated (Box 3)
  - Letters, autograph manuscript signed, from Margaret Conklin to Anne Lundgren, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Letter, typescript signed, from Louis Untermeyer to William Drake, 1975 January 23 (Box 3)
- William Drake Gift, 1890-1984; Series III; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Series III. contains photographs, correspondence, and Teasdale's last will and testament. There are photographs of Teasdale, portraits of Teasdale in artwork, the poets Marianne Moore and Genevieve Taggard, Teasdale's friend Margaret Conklin, and her husband Ernst Filsinger. Correspondence between Margaret Conklin and others relates to Teasdale.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 140.
  Gift of William Drake, 1990.
  - Donor list, undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Sara Teasdale, [circa 1890]-1932, undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs of artistic representations of Sara Teasdale, undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Margaret Conklin, 1932, undated (Box 3)
  - Photograph of Ernst Filsinger, undated (Box 3)
  - Photograph of Marianne Moore, undated (Box 3)
  - Photograph of Genevieve Taggard, [circa 1922] (Box 3)
  - Margaret Conklin correspondence, 1933-1974, undated (Box 3)
  - Letter, autograph manuscript signed, from Mamie Wheless to Marie Teasdale, 1933 March (Box 3)
  - Photograph of the S.S. Sara Teasdale, 1943 October 30 (Box 3)
    Includes letters dated 1944 and 1984
  - Last will and testament, typescript, corrected and signed, 1929 May 13 (Box 3)
- Material from Other Sources, 1905-1931; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  Organized into two subseries for Writings and Correspondence.
  Series IV. contains a small number of writings autograph letters signed by Teasdale.
  Acquired from various sources.
  - Writings
    - "The Carpenter's Son," poem, autograph manuscript, 1913 June (Box 4)
    - "Erinna," poem, typescript, signed, undated (Box 4)
    - [Poems], galley proof, corrected, with annotations by Teasdale, undated (Box 4)
    - "Sappho," poem, autograph manusript, corrected, and typescript carbon, undated (Box 4)
    - "Union Square," poem, typescript mimeograph, initialed, 1911 January (Box 4)
    - "The Potters and the Potters' Wheel" by Frances S. Porcher, essay, printed version, 1905 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Aldis, [Arthur T.], 1922 May 12 (Box 4)
    - Braithwaite, [William S. B.], 1912 March 20 (Box 4)
    - Branch, [Anna Hempstead], 1931 April 7 (Box 4)
    - Johns, Orrick, 1912, undated (Box 4)
      Inclues autograph manuscript drafts of "Darkness at Noon" and "Silence"